Finding Aid for James B. Edmonson (1882-1954) papers 1915-1960 (bulk 1920-1955).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James B. Edmonson papers 1915-1960, 1920-1955
Edmonson, James Bartlett, 1882-1954.
1 oversize volume
4 linear feet
Dean of the School of Education at University of Michigan, 1929-1952. Papers primarily concern his research and work on administration of secondary schools.
851186 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. James B. Edmonson (donor no. 3803 ) in 1961 and 1969, and from the University of Michigan School of Education (donor no. 1220 ) in 1968 and 1970.
The collection is open for research.
James B. Edmonson was born in Parkersburg, Iowa, on December 28, 1882, the son of James Bartlett and Nancy Jane Edmonson. He was married to Bess Chase on August 26, 1914, and had two children, Jane and Donald.
Edmonson received a Bachelor of Arts degree from the University of Michigan in 1906 and his Master's degree in history in 1910. He received the degree of Doctor of Philosophy from the University of Chicago in 1925 in education and history.
He was a teacher in the high school at Ionia, Michigan, and moved from there to the principalship of the high school at Hillsdale. In successive assignments he was principal at Benton Harbor and at Jackson, Michigan. In 1914 he returned to the University of Michigan as Inspector of High Schools and professor of Secondary Education, and he subsequently became the director of the Division of University Inspection of High Schools. In 1929 he became dean of the School of Education and served in that role until his retirement in February 1952. At the conclusion of his retirement furlough in February 1953, he was given the title of Dean Emeritus.
Edmonson wrote numerous articles about educational issues, and was author and co-author of several textbooks on educational administration and high school civics.
He served as secretary (1921-31) and president (1931-32) of the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools. After his retirement, he continued to serve as chairman of the Committee on Athletics of the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, of the Committee on Fraudulent Schools and Colleges of the National Education Association, and as co-chairman of the Canada-United States Committee on Education.
Edmonson had a great interest in railroads and railroading and enjoyed travel. Also, throughout his life he was interested in church affairs and church-related problems of education, building, and finance. He was considered a strong defender of the ethical and spiritual significance of the work done in schools.
James B. Edmonson died in his home in Ann Arbor, Michigan, on June 4, 1954.
The James B. Edmonson collection contains material relating to the career and personal interests of this educator. The collection is organized in five series: Biographical/Personal containing biographical sketches, bibliographies, photographs, and files relating to his involvement with the University of Michigan Presbyterian Corporation; Topical files consisting mainly of writings by Edmonson, correspondence, reports, essays, and other materials on education related subjects, including intercollegiate athletics, the Canada-United States Committee on Education, so-called "diploma mills", and issues affecting secondary school education; selection of term reports from classes taught by Edmonson; textbooks and other publications of Edmonson; and files, 1942-1945, relating to his work with the University War Board
Subjects:
Canada-United States Committee on Education.; College sports--United States.; Diploma mills--United States.; Education--Canada.; Education--United States.; Education, Secondary--United States.; First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Universities and colleges--Accreditation--United States.; University of Michigan. Presbyterian Corporation.; University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. War Board.; World War, 1939-1945--War work--Michigan.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal, contains biographical information, including lists of published works, committee appointments, biographical sketches, tributes, and correspondence. Also included in this section are materials relating to Edmonson's hobby, railroads. A photograph folder contains a small amount of pictures of Edmonson and his colleagues, mostly from the 1950s.
  Edmonson's work with the University of Michigan Presbyterian Corporation is also well documented in Series One. The Corporation succeeded the Tappan Hall Presbyterian Association and represents the first work among Presbyterian college students in a state university. It is affiliated with the Ann Arbor Presbyterian Church. These folders include minutes from the Committee on Student Work, bylaws, Presbyterian Corporation Board of Trustees meeting minutes, and budget information. Although listed with this series, the family scrapbook is shelved as an oversized volume, separate from the collection. It contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, images of Edmonson as a young man, and other items "to revive pleasant memories."
  - General, undated 1920-1957, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1945 (Box 1)
  - Memorials 1954 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Schoolmasters' Club 1952 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Schoolmasters' Club, Letters of Tribute 1952, 1 volume (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1934-1956 (Box 1)
  - Railroads, 1940-1954 (Box 1)
  - Retirement, undated 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1932-1953 (Volume 1)
  - University of Michigan Presbyterian Corporation, undated 1934-1956, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Presbyterian Corporation
    - Board of Trustees, minutes 1952-1954 (Box 1)
- Topical
  The Topical files series consists mainly of the writings of Edmonson on various issues in education, both secondary and college, and also includes correspondence, papers and essays, reports, minutes, and some published material by Edmonson. Some especially significant files include "Intercollegiate Athletics," under which can be found information on the increasing role of sports in colleges and the subsequent educational debate. "Intercollegiate Athletics" also contains a file on the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools pertaining to sports in colleges during the 1950s. A significant amount of information can be found on the "Canada-United States Committee on Education" which was formed to study the quality and quantity of information taught by each country about their neighbor. The "Fraudulent Schools" files contain correspondence and articles on the "diploma mills" of the 1950s, and the efforts to expose them. There are also folders on various aspects of secondary and college teaching and issues relating to public schools.
  - Accreditation of Academic Institutions, undated 1920-1954 (Box 1)
  - Alumni 1953 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors 1953 (Box 1)
  - Black Colleges
    - "Report on a Visit to Bishop College at Marshall, Texas," 1936 (Box 1)
  - Canada-United States Committee on Education
    - General undated, 1942-1954, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - History 1952 (Box 1)
    - Subcommittee on International Understanding 1954 (Box 1)
  - Career Advancement 1949 (Box 1)
  - Children's Rights, undated 1924-1948 (Box 1)
  - College-High School Relations undated, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Community, undated 1921-1945 (Box 1)
  - Community Appraisal, undated 1935-1942 (Box 1)
  - Democracy, undated 1940-1948 (Box 1)
  - The Edison Institute, undated 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Educational Improvement, undated 1950 (Box 1)
  - Educational Policies Commission 1942, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Efficiency of Instruction, undated 1923 (Box 1)
  - Entrance Requirements, Schools, undated 1922-1925 (Box 1)
  - Federal Aid 1937-1953 (Box 1)
  - Fraudulent Schools, undated 1950-1960, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Future of Education, undated 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - G. I. Bill of Educational Rights 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Guidance, undated 1933-1950 (Box 1)
  - Health Education 1920-1938 (Box 1)
  - Higher Education
    - General, undated 1934-1953 (Box 2)
    - Instruction 1924, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Progressive Movements undated (Box 2)
  - Horace Mann League 1948 (Box 2)
  - Human Relations, undated 1923-1952 (Box 2)
  - Intercollegiate Athletics
    - General, undated 1951-1954 (Box 2)
    - "...Conference of Officials of the North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools with Representatives of Intercollegiate Athletic Conferences," 1932 (Box 2)
    - North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, undated 1951 (Box 2)
  - Junior Colleges 1950 (Box 2)
  - Junior High Schools, undated 1925 (Box 2)
  - Leadership 1950 (Box 2)
  - Merit Rating 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Committee on Teacher Education 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - Morale, undated 1928-1949 (Box 2)
  - National Planning for Education, undated 1941-1946 (Box 2)
  - National Recovery Association (NRA), undated 1933-1936 (Box 2)
  - North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools 1924-1953 (Box 2)
    (See also: Intercollegiate Athletics--North Central Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools)
  - Parents, undated 1925-1941 (Box 2)
  - Physical Education, undated 1931-1941 (Box 2)
  - Professional Organizations, undated 1950-1952 (Box 2)
  - Program Planning 1946 (Box 2)
  - Public Education, undated 1921-1951 (Box 2)
  - Public Relations, undated 1925-1949 (Box 2)
  - Pupils
    - Citizenship, undated 1942 (Box 2)
    - Improving Scholarship, undated 1921-1927 (Box 2)
  - Religion and Schools, undated 1923-1954 (Box 2)
  - Reviews, undated 1951 (Box 2)
  - Schools of Education, undated 1925-1951 (Box 2)
  - Secondary Education, undated 1924-1950 (Box 2)
  - Secondary Schools
    - General, undated 1921-1948 (Box 2)
    - Administration
      - General, undated 1923-1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - "Constitutional and Legal Basis of Public School Administration," 1935, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Criticism, undated 1932-1953 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum, undated 1924-1953 (Box 2)
    - Discipline, undated 1920-1954 (Box 2)
    - Instruction, undated 1937-1953 (Box 2)
    - Michigan, undated 1921-1952 (Box 2)
    - "Obstacles to Change...," undated 1931-1933 (Box 2)
    - Occupational Training, undated 1939-1950 (Box 2)
    - Principals, undated 1922-1946 (Box 2)
    - United States, undated 1939-1953 (Box 2)
  - Social Trends undated (Box 2)
  - State Board of Education
    - Extra-Legal Advisory Planning Commission, Report 1935 (Box 2)
  - State Department of Public Instruction 1936 (Box 2)
  - Teachers
    - General, undated 1920-1948 (Box 2)
    - Education of, undated 1920-1952 (Box 2)
    - Employment, undated 1945-1948 (Box 2)
    - Retirement, undated 1915-1944 (Box 2)
    - Salaries, undated 1921-1951 (Box 2)
  - Teaching Profession 1924-1952 (Box 2)
  - Textbooks, undated 1930-1952 (Box 2)
  - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) undated, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan
    - General, undated 1946-1954 (Box 2)
    - Fresh Air Camp 1931-1945 (Box 2)
    - School of Education 1928-1955 (Box 2)
    - Three-Term Plan 1942 (Box 2)
  - World War II, undated 1940-1945 (Box 2)
  - Youth, undated 1935-1944 (Box 2)
- Course Material from Classes Taught by J.B. Edmonson (Selection)
  Contained in a separate series, but directly relating to the career of Edmonson is Course Materials from Classes Taught by J.B. Edmonson (Selection). In three large, bound volumes are term reports written by students enrolled in Edmonson's classes in "State and National Trends in Education," "Administration of Secondary Schools," and "School Law." Titles include, "A Plan for Rural Schools," "The Case For and Against Sex Education in High School," and "Individual Liability of School Board Members."
  - "Term Reports, State and National Trends in Education: Education B195." Summer 1932 (Box 3)
  - "Term Reports in Administration of Secondary Schools: Education B124." 1932 (Box 3)
  - "Term Reports in School Law: Education B225." Part One. Summer 1932 (Box 3)
- Published Works Relating to Education
  Published Works Relating to Education, contains books written or co-authored by Edmonson. The works concern topics relating to secondary education as well as workbooks to be used in secondary school classrooms.
  - Congdon, Wray H. and J.B. Edmonson. The Modern High School and Its Problems: Contributions of Students in Education B124s. Ann Arbor, MI: Edwards Brothers, Inc., 1931 (Box 4)
  - Department of the National Educational Association of Superintendence of the United States. Social Change and Education: Thirteenth Yearbook. Washington, D.C.: The Department, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B., Joseph Roemer and Francis L. Bacon. The Administration of the Modern Secondary School. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. The Legal and Constitutional Bases of the Public School System of Michigan. Unpublished (Box 4)
  - Committee of the Faculty of the School of Education, University of Michigan. The Evaluation of Instruction. Ann Arbor, MI: Bureau of Educational Reference and Research, 1939 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. Problems in Secondary Education. Bloomington, IL: Public School Publishing Company, 1923 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. and Erwin E. Lewis. Problems in the Administration of a School System. Bloomington, IL: Public School Publishing Company, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. and Erwin E. Lewis. Problems in the Administration of a Small School System. Bloomington, IL: Public School Publishing Company, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. and Arthur Dondineau. A Pupil's Workbook in Civics. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1935 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. and Arthur Dondineau. Problems and Tests in Civics. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. and Arthur Dondineau. A Pupil's Workbook in Occupations. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Edmonson, J.B. and Arthur Dondineau. A Pupil's Workbook in Vocations. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1937 (Box 4)
- University War Board
  The University War Board of the University of Michigan files were designated a separate series because they contain not only Edmonson's writings, but also the administrative documents of the board itself. Included are files relating to the University's shift in educational goals during World War II. Found here are writings by Edmonson, minutes of the Board, correspondence, reports, and publications. The "University War Board--Administration" files have been re-foldered, but the original order, as kept in three binders dated January-February, March-September, and October-November, 1942, has been maintained.
  - General, undated 1942-1945, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Administration 1942, 14 folders (Box 4)